So Bante, what is the difference between
um hiring and Otapa
versus just kind of an ambiguous
hindrance of guilt?
>> Why would guilt be a hindrance?
>> I think it would be a hindrance if it's
with regard to things that you don't
have to be guilty about. Mhm.
>> So I mean just take a random example.
Say you feel guilty about not
um killing in a certain instance where
it would have been it would have made
your life better. Something like that.
>> Mhm.
>> Um obviously that's an extreme example
but it's a unambiguous one
>> where guilt would actually be obscuring
what you need to see.
>> Yeah. Well um there's a reason why the
sutas always say that the all these
wholesome factors all these uh qualities
of mind that you have to develop they
depend on right view. So you you can't
just kind of you can't have faith in
random things. You can't have um shame
and remorse in regard to random things.
You can't be mindful of random things.
Compose your mind random things and
understand random things. Those five
faculties have to be guided by a right
view. So you have to then learn what the
criteria are to begin with. Like uh
breaking precepts is what you have to be
ashamed of. Um but you will only be able
to arrive at the right shame if you
understand why breaking precepts is
harmful. Like if you have a goal that
you have to fulfill and then regard even
if it's a worldly goal actually and then
you find yourself doing things that lead
against it the natural result of that is
guilt. It's not even something you have
to fabricate. You just feel like oh I
wanted this and I did the opposite. Uh
so you have to then understand
to be able to to have that actual sense
of shame that's not just a random
fabricated thing. You have to have
developed that connection between
uh breaking the precepts and going
against my goal. Like that connection
needs to be clear. If you're still in
doubt that oh maybe sometimes it's not
an issue. Maybe sometimes the benefit
outweighs the the harm. Then you won't
be able to feel ashamed on the right
level. It has to be basically um the
connection needs to be inseparable
where you're enabled to doubt that if
you do these things you are going
against the training and then if if that
perspective is established
uh the shame will arise naturally.
you would you would then need to cover
it up not to have it. And uh well, how
do you uh establish that perspective?
Well, you have to contemplate it. Like
most people would uh only see the
secondary consequences
of uh why breaking precepts would be
harmful. They would see, oh well, it
leads to the harm of others. It kind of
creates trouble for me. um leads to I
don't know loss of wealth whatever
you want to see you want to understand
it in such a way that you couldn't even
in the most fortunate circumstance even
if you actually end up helping everyone
including yourself and producing nothing
but gain
that even then doing these things would
be harmful for you and the only way to
understand that is uh by understanding
greed aversion and delusion, seeing
those as internal things that basically
you're you're chaining yourself to
simply by committing these actions. So,
it's like a like a curse that you're
putting on yourself that even though
regardless of anything else you might
do, you're training yourself
you're training yourself
to crave for pleasant feeling. Training
yourself to crave against pleasant
feeling, training yourself to resist uh
lack of activity, which means that's
going to come back and bite you either
late. Well, not only come back and bite
you right now, cultivating those
tendencies is unpleasant. How do you
know? Well, don't break precepts after
you broke precepts. And you will see
that your mind was already in a bad
state. It was simply being covered up by
the all the distractions you were
engaging with. So, you will then realize
having this regardless of what else
happens, having this mental state is
harmful in and of itself. And that's how
you start making that inseparable
connection. like yeah all the other stuff remains.
like yeah all the other stuff remains.
You don't have to deny it but sometimes
breaking precepts could lead to uh
mundane benefit
like killing in some instance you could
>> well nobody would do it if it didn't.
Yeah, you you could save millions of
lives by killing one person factually,
but none of that will be able to
override the perspective of what you're
actually doing on that internal level
when you decide to kill.
>> So, you should try to make that your
metric rather than just guilt about this
or that.
>> Yeah. So like I said, when that
connection is established, when you you
you see yourself
um
chaining yourself to these unpleasant
mental states automatically by doing
these actions, you won't be able to not
feel guilt
cuz it's like who would knowingly harm
themselves. Whenever somebody goes and
does something that's harmful, it's
because they were focused on the
gratifying aspect of that action, you
can't do something while at the same
time being prioritizing the perception
of danger in it.
So if if if that is what you put
forward, the perception of danger that
is independent of any circumstances that
cannot change no matter what happens
externally, then you can't but feel
guilt. You can't but be rightly uh
apprehensive which is the the one translation fora
which is the the one translation fora
like apprehension of wrongdoing. Uh you
you you wouldn't be able to not feel
that in regard to those actions because
it would be obvious the harm is what's
being highlighted is what being put
first. So if you are feeling guilty and its
So if you are feeling guilty and its
reference point is your idea of what the
practice is, does that make it always a
good metric?
>> Well, no. You have to um first clarify
those ideas about what the practice is.
So yeah, for example, some people might
feel guilty about not meditating.
That's wrong. like it's it's
that implies a wrong view of what the
practice is because it's prioritizing
this random observance
whereas what you would have to be
ashamed of is am I engaging with greed
aversion and delusion so many people
would have that upside down they would
be more ashamed of not meditating than
they would be about not being celibate
so there is no way to get around the
need to clarify your views and clarify
the what you're actually trying to develop.
what you're actually trying to develop.
That's why you can't have uh right
intention without right view first. So
you have to um clarify what nibbana is
for example like what is the liberation
that you're striving for. Most people
have completely misguided ideas about
what that is and they don't see that
it's about abandoning greed version and
delusion. It's an event that can happen
to you or not happen to you. Therefore,
you would be ashamed of not doing these
random things that could have led to it
by some unknown connection. Whereas, if
you understood that literally as the
Buddha said says it, Nibbana is the
freedom from greed aversion and
delusion, from lust, aversion, and and
ignorance, you you wouldn't be able to
not be ashamed of actual lust, aversion,
and ignorance.
and being yeah being ashamed of these
other things
because of your unclarified misguided
ideas about wood practices would
actively take away from the right shame
like you can't be ashamed of both
relevant and irrelevant things at the
same time.
So even if even if you were to let's say
never break a precept
but your criteria for shame isn't in
that area like when you break precepts
or if you were to break precepts
precepts you would end up finding
excuses um kind of absolving yourself from from
um kind of absolving yourself from from
the issue saying oh well um you know I I
can always do better next time. you
don't allow yourself to feel that as oh
categorically I should not have done
that that was a mistake. If you don't if
if that's not what's going to happen
then even if you don't end up breaking
precepts you're not headed in the right
direction because it means you're not again
because it means you're not again
without right view without having the
right perspective of what is wholesome
and unh wholesome nothing else can be
practiced there's a s where the Buddha says that
there's a s where the Buddha says that
when somebody starts with wrong
intention whatever they do sorry with
wrong view whatever they do by body
speech or mind is polluted
So that's why external adherence to the
precepts is not really the criteria.
It's whether would you ask yourself
would you in every possible instance
where you intentionally broke a precept
feel ashamed.
If there's an instance where that
wouldn't be the case then your idea of
what practice is is wrong. It's taking
you in a different direction.
It would just be trying to cover up the
shame that you would feel on account of
breaking the precept which seems like
>> you may not even see it as cover up.
It's like you're just looking elsewhere
as your goal. So you feel ashamed of
>> not living up to that wrong goal that
has nothing to do with what the Buddhist
practice actually is.
>> So it's not really a matter of choice.
It's like if you have the right aim,
shame in regard to going against that
aim is natural. It's not something you
have to fabricate.
And then yeah, if you feel shame in
regard to that, well, um, how do you
make sure that it doesn't go overboard?
Well, ask yourself,
what is your shame leading to? Like is
it is it fortifying your intention to
never engage in those actions again?
Or is it kind of making you feel like it
doesn't really matter because you're
worthless? Like you're kind of just uh
leaning towards self-loathing.
If that's the case, then that's not
actual guilt. Like if it's if it's the
real guilt that that is Hiotaa that the
Buddha described as the protectors of
the world then it couldn't possibly be
leading you in the direction of
transgression in the direction of doing
it again.
So that's how you know it's like
um
it would always be taking you in the
direction of
not repeating those actions which is why
the Buddha didn't say uh monks um be
careful of shame and remorse. Don't cultivate
of shame and remorse. Don't cultivate
shame and remorse too much. He said um
it was two those are two of the five
faculties that if a noble disciple
cultivates they will become an arat on
the same level in fact more primordial
than uh mindfulness
and wisdom because if you're not afraid
at other random things it's not going to
be directed at I should never engage
with creative aversion and delusion not
having that mindfulness, you couldn't
possibly achieve the right composure,
which is a mind free from greater
diversion and delusion. And without
right composure, you couldn't possibly
achieve the right understanding, which
will make you incapable of doing those
things again once and for all.